[Music]
Professor Dave and CH here we know what
mass spectrometry is and how it works so
now let's get a closer look at Mass
Spectra and see what kind of information
we can get from these in the way of
characterizing compounds to determine
their structure as we recall on a Mass
Spectrum we can take the horizontal axis
to be representative of the molecular
mass of these fragments and by
identifying possible fragments based on
molecular mass we can corroborate
molecular structures for example take a
look at this Mass Spectrum for acetone
when acetone is broken up into fragments
there are only a few possibilities so we
should be able to assign these Peaks by
looking at the molecular masses first we
should note that some of the sample
makes it through without being broken
apart so when we look at the rightmost
data we can presume that this includes
the molecular ion Peak so this is
acetone which is ionized but intact
that's why it shows up at 58 because
that's the molecular mass of acetone it
is worth noting that some molecules
fragment so easily that none of the
molecule makes it to the detector intact
so the molecular ion Peak is not present
but usually it will be present we will
also find what is called the m+1 Peak at
59 this is due to the relative abundance
of carbon
since around 1% of all carbon atoms are
carbon 13 then some small proportion of
acetone molecules will have a carbon 13
nuide somewhere in the molecule giving
it a mass of 59 most of the very small
Peaks found on a Mass Spectrum are
associated with fragments that contain
one of the less abundant isotopes of a
particular element so it is good to
identify them but they do not represent
the bulk of the relevant information the
taller the peak the greater the
abundance of the fragment that is
responsible for it so let's now look at
what is called the base Peak this refers
to the tallest or most intense Peak on
the Spectrum which is set to 100% and
all other Peaks will be relative to this
value in this case the base Peak occurs
at 43 it is easy to identify this as the
fragment that remains if one methyl
group has been removed a methyl group
has a mass of 15 so subtracting 15 from
58 gives us 43
the last major Peak occurs at 15 and
given what we just said about methyl
groups this is also easy to identify as
the methyl group itself and as we said
the rest of the small Peaks will
typically correspond to variations of
the major fragments involving different
isotopes which explains their very low
abundance to further solidify this
concept take a look at the Mass Spectrum
for straight chain hexane we get a
molecular ion Peak at 86 which
corresponds with the molecular mass then
we can see Peaks that correspond with
progressively smaller fragments as we
begin to remove one carbon at a time so
there is a pentle cation AAL propyl and
ethyl with the appropriate masses this
is more straightforward as it is a
simple hydrocarbon but specific
functional groups have characteristic
types of fragmentation that makes them
possible to identify as
well so getting a Mass Spectrum is a
great way to determine the molecular
formula of a compound and its structure
rure we simply identify the molecular
ion Peak to find its molecular mass and
then analyze the rest of the data to
identify potential fragments putting
these fragments together to give
something with the correct molecular
mass is likely to yield the correct
structure Professor Dave for che see you
next time